A Guide to the Charles James Apperley [Nimrod] Papers 1797-1851
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Charles James Apperley [Nimrod] Papers 1797-1851
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11080
1043 items
This collection consists of the unpublished correspondence of Charles James Apperley ["Nimrod"] (1778-1843), primarily with John Pittman, editor of The Sporting Magazine, and other members of the staff, and other papers pertaining to the magazine, bound into eleven volumes, and one volume of financial documents. Apperley is ranked as the greatest hunting correspondent of all time by A.H. Higginson in British and American Sporting Authors.
These papers were collected by John M. Schiff.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The University of Virginia Library purchased these papers from James Cummins, Bookseller, New York City, on March 3, 1993.
Provenance
This collection was formerly owned and bound into volumes by the collector John M. Schiff.
Biographical/Historical Information
Charles James Apperley (1778-1843), "Nimrod," was born at Plasgronow, near Wrexham, Denbighshire, second son of Thomas Apperley, tutor to Sir Watkin Williams Wynn. In 1790, Apperley entered Rugby and stayed until 1798; After leaving he became a cornet in Sir Watkin Wynn's Ancient Light British Dragoons, a regiment of fencible cavalry, with which he served in the suppression of the Irish rebellion. Returning to England in 1801, he married Winifred, the daughter of William Wynn of Peniarth (the cousin of Sir Watkin), Merionethshire, and settled at Hinkley in Leicestershire. In 1804, Apperley moved to Bilton Hall, near Rugby, where he hunted with the Quorn, the Pytchley, and the Warwickshire hounds. From Bilton he moved in 1809 to Bitterley Court in Shropshire, and accepted a commission as captain in the Nothinghamshire militia, known as the Sherwood Foresters. Later he moved to Brewood in Staffordshire, and then to Beaurepaire House in Hampshire, where he lost much capital in farming experiments. His first paper in The Sporting Magazine was an article about "Foxhunting in Leicestershire" in January 1822. Apperley continued a fruitful association with the magazine and its editor, John Pittman, until 1828, when he stopped writing for the publication. To escape disputes over his finances, connected with the settling of the Pittman estate, Apperley fled to Calais, France in 1830, where he became a regular member of the staff of the Sporting Review. He also began a series of sporting memoirs and reminiscences, and in 1835, he published three articles, including "The Road," "Melton Mowbray," and "The Turf". Nimrod returned to England in 1842, dying in Upper Belgrave Place, Pimlico, on May 19, 1843.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of the unpublished correspondence of Charles James Apperley ["Nimrod"] (1778-1843), primarily with John Pittman, editor of The Sporting Magazine, and other members of the staff, and other papers pertaining to the magazine, bound into eleven volumes and containing ca. 1,043 items, ca. 1797, 1818-1839, 1847-1851, and one volume of financial documents. Apperley is ranked as the greatest hunting correspondent of all time by A.H. Higginson in British and American Sporting Authors.
An experienced horseman, Apperley wrote his lively anecdotes and stories mainly for The Sporting Magazine, the greatest sports journal of its day, from 1822 to 1828, under the pseudonym "Nimrod," reaching a large audience and providing an accurate picture of 19th century English sports, especially those of fox hunting and horse racing. Many of the letters in the collection deal with Apperley's often stormy relations with the magazine and its publisher; his financial difficulties despite constant loans and an ever increasing salary; his own personal horse-dealing interests, complaints about the quality of other writers' work; suggestions for raising the price of the magazine; details of his hunting tours, complete with expense reports; gossip; praise of himself and his popularity; suggestions for articles on cock fighting, fencing, pheasant breeding and others; and sprinkled throughout with names of royalty, nobility, and sporting personalities.
Apperley's relationship with The Sporting Magazine and its editor was extremely variable. During his tenure as hunting correspondent, the immense popularity of his reports of hunts and hunting men tripled the magazine's circulation. But his financial demands on the magazine's editor and owner John Pittman were so great that after Pittman's death on November 27, 1827, the publication, burdened with debt, had to be sold. Apparently, Apperley moved to Calais, France, in November 1830 (see volume seven, page 83) to avoid the importunities of the widow, Mary Ann Pittman, and the estate's executors, who were trying to recover money advanced to Apperley by Pittman and already spent.
The collection consists of two distinct but intertwined groups of papers. One is the correspondence of Apperley, approximately 584 letters, signed, mostly to John Pittman, and after Pittman's death, to various individuals concerning the claims of his estate. Also present is a manuscript by Apperley, Road Work, and two pages of corrected proofs, both in volume one. General subjects in these letters include: Apperley's comments about the quality of the reporting in The Sporting Magazine which is lacking from "real practical observation"; an emphasis on his own qualifications as a sporting correspondent; his agricultural pursuits; innovative ideas like watering down race courses; potential subjects for articles such as cockfighting, angling, fencing, pheasant breeding, etc.; Apperley's various literary projects; details of hunting tours and expense reports; and constant financial appeals. The financial arguments continue after Pittman's death and Apperley's resignation from the magazine on October 10, 1828, well into the next decade.
The second group contains 459 letters and documents concerning The Sporting Magazine, and includes drafts of letters to Apperley, correspondence from the magazine's contributors, and legal documents detailing the confusion which affected the magazine after Pittman's death, partially attributable to Apperley's financial demands. Items include: expense reports, drafts of solicitors' letters, an enumeration of subscribers to reimburse Apperley for expenses incurred in his support of fox-hunting (1830 Apr 2), a letter from Lord Palmerston regretting that he could not stay a legal proceeding against Apperley (1824 Jun 23), correspondence to the staff of The Sporting Magazine from attorneys, readers, potential correspondents, and two letters from R.S. Surtees about writing under another name.
Contents List
  VOLUME ONE
- Volume One ca. 1821-1823, 39 items mounted on 63 pages
  Contains a color engraving of Nimrod by E. Finden in the front, two pages of corrected proofs for an article in The Sporting Magazine, and a fourteen and a half page manuscript "Road Work" by Charles James Apperley (Nimrod), with corrections and deletions throughout, concerning "everything relating to working a coach through a country." Nimrod defines several of the technical terms, "working a coach is called horsing it," discusses considerations in horsing a coach, the division of the coach's earnings, the inequity of tolls paid by stage coaches compared to steamers, "so many of their old customers patronize the tea kettles and forsake the road," and praises the contributions of John Loudon McAdam to the betterment of British roads giving a brief history of his career.
  Volume one also contains Apperley's letter of approach to The Sporting Magazine offering to write for the publication and furnishing his qualifications, December 10, 1821, "I have long been a reader of your magazine and have for some time observed, in common with my friends, a great falling off in its contents, for the want of information derived from a proper source; that is to say - from the real practical observation of one who witnesses and has witnessed the scenes which your work (to create the interest of your readers) ought to contain. .... With respect to my pretensions to your notice I have to observe that I have been an owner of race horses up to the present year, as also an attendant with [the] best hounds in all the celebrated counties up to the present season - have a large circle of sporting friends with whose private entertainments I am well acquainted, and my own connections in life are of the highest class." In his second letter to the magazine, December 12, 1821, Apperley continues, "I think I could materially alter the character of your work, and increase its sale very considerably by making it the vehicle for that kind of information which is so much sought after in the sporting world - add to which, I know the private history of almost every man who is, or who has been, conspicuous amongst us." A latter letter, October 16, [1822], in the same volume attacks one of his predecessors at the magazine, "My friend Corbet thinks old L[awrence] and his chaff sickened them [the readers] and certainly on looking over your kind present [past numbers of The Sporting Magazine,] I do find a great deal that had better been blown away. However, we must remember he has been an old servant, & perhaps, once useful."
  Articles mentioned in volume 1 as sent or in preparation:
  agriculture article for The County Chronicle page 18
  "Basingstoke Race" page 11
  "Cocking" page 7
  "Condition of Hunters" pages 20, 28
  "Croxton Park, the Mostyn Hunt, and the H.H. Races" (1822 Apr) page 54
  Dandyism article pages 11, 17, 19
  Devon Fox Hunting page 6
  Earl of Derby Stag Hounds page 7
  "Feast of Wit" pages 11, 28
  fencing book & article pages 24, 28
  fishing pages 24, 28
  "Hampshire Hunting" pages 11, 54
  "Hare Hunting" page 10
  "His Royal Highness The Duke of York" in 1822 June & July numbers pages 12-14, 32
  "Hunting in Leicestershire" in Lord Foley's time pages 12, 44
  Mostyn Hunt page 54
  "Nabob's Racing Calendar" page 10
  "Partridge Shooting" page 10
  "Pleasure" page 44
  riding to hounds pages 6, 38, 41, 42, 43, 45, 46, 48, 49
  "The Road" pages 10, 11, 30
  "Sir John Dashwood's Harriers" page 11
  snipe shooting page 38
  "Sporting Anecdotes" page 11
  stag hunting pages 25, 26
  veterinary surgeons & farriers page 40
  "Warwickshire" pages 12, 18, 19, 30, 41, 42, 43, 45
  woodcocks page 28
  Subjects mentioned in volume 1:
  Apperley's advice for advancing the circulation of the magazine pages 20, 21, 23, 42, 45
  Apperley's farm pages 46, 48
  Apperley's handwriting - no need for proofs if he writes more legibly page 15
  Apperley's financial difficulties - (who also suggests charging more for SM p. 39) pages 43, 47, 48, 49, 50, 52, 53, 57, 60, 63
  Apperley's requests for money or an increase in salary pages 17, 18, 23, 29, 30, 36, 41, 58
  Apperley's request to publish Nimrod's letters in The Sporting Magazine as a separate volume page 58
  Apperley - death of his sister page 44
  ashes as a manure page 58
  Berkeley Hunt Day page 16
  breeding pheasants page 41
  William Chute pages 24, 26, 28
  colored engraving of Nimrod on frontispiece
  Sir John Cope page 49
  Vincent Corbet, Master of Hounds, wants a plate illustration of, with his grey horse & hound Trojan page 12
  Vincent Corbet & Mervinia page 41
  C. Day, stables of page 16
  Lord Derby's hounds page 35
  Duke of York - request for information about trainer, rider of his light weights, and if he was on the turf before 1800 pages 12-14, 32
  Euphrates purchased by Mr. Charlton page 19
  Newton Fellows, "Brother of the crazy Lord Portsmouth" & Master of Fox Hounds pages 20, 26
  Lord Foley page 12
  Lord [Forester] page 6, his leap at the hunt of the Duke of Rutland page 43
  [Stephen ?] Goodall - need a portrait of page 28
  greyhounds page 47
  Hambledon Foxhounds page 29
  Hambledon Hunt Races, Apperley's win in 2nd heat and his black eye pages 47, 55
  the Hampshire Club pages 19, 26
  horse breeding pages 21, 23
  Colonel Jolliffe page 35
  [Warwick ?] Lake (Master of the Horse to the Duke of York) page 13
  [Fox Lane?], sale of stud horses and dogs at York page 43
  Leicestershire trip page 36
  Lichfield Meeting - horses Master Henry & [Anti?]-Radical page 34
  Mr. Lucas & his "flattering offer" to Apperley page 56
  McAdam, John Loudon, "the Colossus of Roads" and his contributions to British roads pages 2-4
  Melton [Hunt] page 48
  Moses and the [St. Leger Race ?] pages 11, 19
  Sir Thomas Mostyn page 28
  Mr. Nicoll, Master of New Forest [Fox] Hounds page 29
  Oatlands Stakes, request to find origin of pages 13-14
  Philo Junius style of writing by Apperley pages 10-11
  John Pittman suffering from gout page 48
  John Pittman's horses are ready at Apperley's page 59
  Mr. [Poplin], Apperley's comments re earlier contributor to The Sporting Magazine page 8
  qualifications of Apperley to correct some of the deficiencies of the magazine pages 8-9
  "The Road and Field," tentative title of Apperley's book page 9
  Road Work manuscript pages 1-5
  Tom Smith page 12
  The Sporting Magazine corrected page proofs (pages 179 & 182) w/letter on verso, page 6
  stage coaches - financial aspects page 1
  Lord Stanford & his stud horse page 19
  steamers taking passenger traffic away from stage coaches page 1
  Mr. Villebois of the Hampshire Hunt pages 26, 29
  watering race courses page 14
  Mr. West page 61
  Mr. West's jockey, Langer, died as a result of a fall while riding at Warwick last year page 54
  W. Wynn (brother-in-law to Apperley) to Pittman, giving security for 300 pounds page 52
  VOLUME TWO
- Volume Two, 103 items mounted on 88 pages
  Volume two, ca. 1823-1824, consists of 103 items mounted on 88 pages, and is as much concerned with Apperley's financial difficulties, his schemes for expanding the readership of The Sporting Magazine, and his negotiations with John Pittman for an increase in salary or loans of money, as it is with authoring articles for publication. An example of this is a letter from Apperley to Pittman, August 5, 1823, where he is proposing new terms for his services, including agricultural articles, "This could enable me to keep one hunter, and go some way towards keeping a sort of a groom (one of all works) which would contribute not only to my comfort but respectability, which should not be altogether lost sight of." He goes on to say that he must also have a pony for parcels, copies of the provincial papers, money to attend the principal agricultural fairs, and be recompensed for the money lost by having to keep his hunting horse at hand.
  Articles mentioned in volume two as sent or in preparation:
  Apperley's detailed plan for future articles pages 49, 51
  Ascot Races -error in Apperley's account pages 25, 31
  "Bird Catching" page 28
  "Bit of a Jockey" criticism by Apperley page 2
  Buckle's biography page 61
  "Cheetah Hunt" (in 1823 Sep) pages 26, 27, 33
  "Chester Races" (in 1824 May) pages 59, 60, 61
  Comparison between Scotch & English farming page 85
  "Condition of Hunters" pages 28, 33, 48, 65, 76, 77, 79, 81, 85, 86
  "coursing" letter (dog racing) page 80
  "Feast of Wit" page 28
  fishing page 70
  the game laws page 46
  grouse shooting page 16
  "Hawkers Review" pages 76, 77
  "His Majesty's Hounds" [King George IV] (in 1824 Feb) pages 3, 4, 48, 70
  horse course remarks page 35
  Kentish fox hunting (in 1823 May) pages 32, 35
  "Liverpool Harriers" page 58
  memoir of Sir Charles [Bamfylde ?] (in 1823) page 32
  "Mr. Yeatman's Harriers" (in 1823 Aug) page 28
  "North Devon Stag Hunting" pages 74, 75, 77
  "the Old Forester" letter (in 1824 Oct) page 84
  "On the Road" page 77-79
  the pavement of London page 33
  pigeon shooting rules page 58
  "Pugilistic Ring" errors page 2
  "Riding to Hounds" pages 10, 11, 28, 33
  "The Road" pages 66, 71
  Surrey Hunt & fox hounds pages 1, 2, 4, 5, 6, 13, 25, 29, 44, 48
  training page 69
  "The Tour" pages 14, 15
  "The Union Hounds" (in 1824 Jan) pages 4, 9
  vascular disease page 73
  "Warwickshire" pages 11, 32, 70, 72, 82
  Woodcock Shooting page 76
  Subjects mentioned in volume 2:
  [Rudolph] Ackermann (1764-1834) page 1
  agricultural articles page 14
  Lord Anson pages 38, 39
  Apperley's advice for advancing the circulation of the magazine pages 5, 6, 8, 11, 12, 21, 21, 22, 49, 78
  Apperley elected a member to the old Hampshire Club page 11
  Apperley's expenses page 82
  Apperley's fall at Brighton page 56
  Apperley's farm & stock pages 14, 20, 33, 52, 53, 63
  Apperley's financial difficulties pages 11, 14, 18, 19, 20, 21, 23, 29, 44, 49, 55
  Apperley's plan for future articles pages 49, 51, 63, 77
  Apperley's sons, one to the East Indies & the other writing for SM pages 12, 70
  Apperley wants Nimrod's letters published by themselves in a volume page 4
  Mr. Atherton, debt owed to page 81
  Mr. Baring page 76
  Duke of Beaufort page 82
  Beaurepaire Farm Account page 40
  Blandford Races pages 69, 76
  Brighton Races pages 30, 51, 56
  Jack Bun[ie?] "of sporting notoriety" page 76
  Cheltenham meeting pages 71, 73, 74
  [William] Chute pages 53, 54, 70, 77, 86
  Professor Coleman contradicted by Apperley page 1
  competitor's comments about Nimrod page 54
  [Sir John] Cope pages 53, 57
  Vincent Corbet pages 26, 33
  Mr. Davis told Nimrod that the King read his letters in SM page 48, 84
  Charles Day, the jockey pages 69, 73
  Lord Derby pages 25, 30, 44, 48, 51, 52, 53, 59, 60, 70
  Devon pages 81,82,84, 87
  distemper "raging" page 81
  Lord Egremont's stud horse pages 49, 51
  Epsom stables page 25
  John James Farquharson (1784-1871) page 76
  Newton Fellows pages 74, 81
  Lord Fortescue & his hounds page 76
  Thomas Gifford page 59
  Sir Bellingham Graham pages 38, 59, 82
  greyhounds pages 8, 84
  hare hunting pages 1, 2
  the Reverend Harrison page 49
  hawking information page 1
  hunting counties - Apperley has material for at least articles on seventeen more (listed page 11), page 44
  Colonel Jolliffe & his fox hounds pages 1, 2, 4, 30, 48, 54
  Mr. Kenyon page 32
  [King George IV] - Nimrod rode in his company for almost two hours page 48
  Mr. Lawrence pages 74, 84
  Leicestershire page 82
  John Lockley and his horse Confidence pages 45, 46, 66, 75, 79, 80, 82, 83, 84
  London's floods page 60
  Mr. Lucas page 69
  Sir Thomas Mostyn page 82
  Mr. Mullins & his harriers pages 77, 86, 87
  John Mytton pages 59, 82
  Newmarket page 69
  Oatlands page 31
  Mr. Oswald - has got a whipper-in for him, the son of Sir Thomas Mostyn's huntsman page 37
  Devon Parsons pages 28, 35
  Mr. Peel, brother to the Secretary page 38
  Lord Plymouth pages 62, 71, 74, 76
  praise for Nimrod page 50
  Prosper belonging to Lord Derby pages 51, 54
  Sir Richard Puleston (Master of Fox Hounds) married Vincent Corbet's daughter pages 11, 28, 54, 70, 82
  Rev. John Russell page 69
  Mr. Tattersall page 79
  George Templer (1781-1843) pages 69, 81, 82
  John Warde (1751-1838) pages 51, 54, 66, 67, 69, 70, 82, 84, 86
  Welsh parson in Devon page 86
  Mr. West page 25
  Tom [Whipcord ?] page 79
  Colonel Wyndham's hounds pages 49, 50, 51
  Mr. Wynne's estate to be sold, (August 1823) page 17
  Mr. Young pages 25, 41, 51, 60
  VOLUME THREE
- Volume Three 1824-1825, ca. 84 items mounted on 75 pages
  Volume three of the Nimrod letters, ca. 1824-1825, consists of ca. 84 items mounted on 75 pages. Apperley writes of his and Pittman's relationship, "I have often thought it was an evil day that brought you and myself together. Our whole career has been one of trouble, perplexity, & everything unpleasant to our feelings as gentlemen" (n.d., page 20). In this volume, he also asks Pittman to release him from his contract, "I am getting very sick of labouring, as I have done these last few years, and doing myself no good. I have a great regard for you, but 'number one' will predominate" (n.y. May 17, page 27).
  Articles mentioned in volume 3 as sent or in preparation:
  Austrian hunting page 66
  "Basingstoke Races" page 33
  biographical sketches of prominent jockey proposal page 57
  "Breeding the Race Horse" page 31
  "Condition of Hunters" pages 3, 17, 19, 21, 26, 31
  "Coursing" pages 11, 12
  "Eclipse with his Jockey, Jack Oakley, going over the Beacon Course" page 25
  "A Fortnight With Mr. Warde's Hounds" (in 1824 Dec) page 11
  Leicestershire letter page 28
  "The New Year" (in 1825 Jan) page 17
  "Mr. Bryant Corcoran. Aged 73 A Celebrated Character in Lord Derby's Hunt" page 33
  ornithology (in 1825 Jan) page 17
  preservation of game and the destruction of foxes page 44
  "the Regatta" pages 67, 70
  "Riding to Hounds" page 19
  "The Road" pages 26, 30, 31
  "The Tour" pages 60, 61, 62, 64, 66, 68, 74, 75
  Villebois, the Hampshire Hunt, and the Hambledon (in 1825 Jan) pages 17, 18, 63
  Yeatman's hounds, account of pages 25, 33
  Subjects mentioned in volume 3:
  Lord Anson & his hounds page 36
  Apperley's advice for advancing the circulation of the magazine pages 5, 10, 15, 68
  Apperley asks Pittman for a release from his contract & other negotiations pages 27, 47, 48
  Apperley's farm & horses pages 15, 16, 27, 29, 35, 48, 50, 71
  Apperley's financial difficulties pages 3, 8, 9, 19, 24, 25, 27, 29, 31, 47, 48, 51, 58, 60, 66, 68
  Apperley's sons page 23
  Ascot Races page 30
  Barmoor page 1
  Mr. Smith Barry pages 40, 41, 42
  Duke of Beaufort pages 34, 58
  young Berkeley's stag hounds pages 8, 10
  Mr. [Henry?] Bigg page 4
  the Blandford races pages 21, 33
  Brighton Harriers page 32
  Lord Brudenell page 14
  Captain Burton page 42
  Billy Butler page 44
  [Harrison?] Carr page 32
  censorship page 1
  [Letchmere?] Charlton pages 21, 33
  John Codrington pages 4, 7
  Harvey Combe pages 22, 34, 35
  Colonel Cook's book on hunting page 72
  Sir John Cope pages 22, 75
  coursing (dog racing) page 2
  [Guy?] Crane page 66
  Croxton Park Races pages 35, 39, 42
  Mr. Davis pages 2, 12
  Lord Derby pages 53, 57
  East Sussex page 32
  Exton Park Races page 38
  John James Farquharson pages 15, 33
  Newton Fellows pages 16, 21, 57, 59
  the Rev. Fulwar Fowle page 13
  Sir Bellingham Graham pages 36, 57, 65, 75
  Hambledon hounds pages 16, 17
  Mr. T. Heathcote page 75
  hounds visited by Apperley, list of page 43
  hunting counties page 10
  inns listed by Apperley where Pittman should try to sale copies of The Sporting Magazine page 5
  Colonel Jolliffe pages 53, 57
  Chief Justice Kenyon page 14
  Lord Kintore page 40
  Mr. Lawrence pages 23, 31, 63
  Leeds page 1
  Lewes Harriers page 32
  John Lockley & his horse Confidence pages 5, 7, 21, 46
  Lord Lonsdale page 37
  Mr. Lucas pages 15, 33
  Mr. Maxse pages 41, 42
  Melton Races pages 37, 65
  Lord Molyneux page 40
  Mr. Moore, son of the Archbishop of Canterbury, page 41
  John Mytton pages 26, 30, 31
  New Forest hounds page 4
  Mr. Nicoll pages 43, 47, 75
  Nim North's letter [Mr. Sitwell] pages 46, 47, 59
  North Devon stag hounds page 3
  [Mr. George Osbaldeston? (1787-1866)] page 37
  Philip Payne, the Duke of Beaufort's huntsman, page 58
  Sir Richard Puleston pages 5, 10, 66, 72
  Quorn Hounds page 37
  Captain Ross pages 30, 37
  Mr. Shaw page 3
  Mr. [Tom] Smith & his hounds pages 2, 17, 37
  Sir Thomas Stanley page 21
  Mr. Strickland page 3
  Parson Strode page 33
  Sussex & Surrey page 22
  Sir Richard [Sutton?] & his hounds page 38
  Mr. Tattersall pages 30, 31
  Mr. [Henry?] Taylor & his hounds page 7
  Mr. [George?] Templer page 21
  Vagus, a correspondent to The Sporting Magazine offended at Nimrod page 23
  Mr. Villebois pages 13, 14, 16, 18, 70
  General Sir Hussey Vivian, Equerry to the King, pages 4, 38, 44
  John Warde pages 4, 5, 11, 13, 22, 43, 75
  Charles Wright page 57